All right, welcome to 2026.
So here's a section of our internal strategy
presentation
to talk to you about where we're going.
Okay, Evry is the only subscription that you
need
to stay at the edge of AI.
That's what we're building.
We have three main components of the business.
We do ideas, so that's a daily newsletter
about AI.
We've got apps, so we have four different
AI apps
that help you write with AI, help you
email with AI,
help you organize your files with AI,
does speech-to-text with AI.
Then we have training, so we do camps
and courses
where we teach you about how to use
these tools
like CloudCode or Codex in a really hands
-on way.
We do that all under one subscription.
And we build things in this loop where,
at the start of the loop, we live
in the future.
So we're all of us, it's this really
cool creative playground
where all of us are using all these
tools every day.
It's AI first in every way.
Writing code into a code editor, you're weird.
So we're living in the future.
We write what we see.
Writing, I think, is the soul of Evry,
and by articulating the future that you're living
in,
you bring that future into being
because you can now talk about it
with the people that you work with.
And so we write in order to make
that future visible
to each other and to the people who
read us.
And one of the consequences of that is
it makes it really easy to tell what's
missing,
and then we go build that.
And that becomes all the apps that we
make.
Quora, which is an email agent,
or Monologue, which is a speech-to-text
app.
These are all things that come from our
own needs.
And then we teach what works.
So we take all of that stuff,
and we teach it in camps and courses,
and we do big enterprise deals
where we do trainings to teach people how
to use AI.
So that's the quick background.
I actually did that whole background for the
team, too,
because after 10 days of vacation,
who knows what?
I barely remember what we do.
This is such a cool time
because 2025 was a huge breakout year for
us.
We hit $3 million in total revenue,
which is 3x growth.
We hit $2 million in ARR,
which is, again, 3x growth.
So that's amazing.
And it's just,
I've been running this business for six years,
so having a year like this,
it's just, we finally hit it.
I also feel like we really cemented our
status
where people think of us
and the vibe checks that we do.
Whenever a new model comes out
or a new product comes out,
they think, what is every's take,
which is really important to me.
And I think we've done a really good
job
of having these hands-on vibe checks
on the day it comes out
that tell us what you need to pay
attention
and what you don't.
And we also have four products in market.
And that's crazy.
We're a team of about 20 people
and we have four separate software products
that we run.
We also have our own custom CMS
that runs our website.
And we have a consulting business.
And that's just like crazy shape
for a business to have.
So I'm super proud of that.
And it sets us up for 2026
where I want to double down again.
Our current plan is to 3x our revenue
again.
So that would take us to about
6 million in ARR
and 10 million overall revenue,
which I think is really doable.
The growth from last year was purely organic.
So I think we have a very good
shot
to do this or better.
The next thing that we're going to do
is double down on a unified platform
and ecosystem.
So right now,
all the apps and the content,
they all live in separate silos.
And what we're doing in 2026
is we're going to build
a unified platform layer
where all the apps can talk to each
other.
And we build a centralized idea
of who you are and what you care
about
that makes all the apps better
and also makes the content
that we write better for you.
And then we're going to be fully agent
native.
This is something I'll talk about
a little bit more deeply later on.
But I think being agent native
is a new kind of software development
where apps that are agent native
are basically cloud code
and all the UI,
all the buttons.
It just kicks off an agent
to do all the work
instead of having code manually written
that gets executed.
And I really think
we're in a moment for that right now.
And we're moving all of our software
to be fully agent native
over the next couple months.
Here's what I told the team
about what it looks like
if things are working.
One is by the end of Q1,
if our products can talk to each other.
So we're going to have
Quora talking to Spiral.
When Quora wants to compose an email,
it can talk to Spiral,
which is our writing agent,
and ask it to write something great
or ask it for a writing style.
When Monologue,
which is our smart dictation app,
when you're using it,
it has a custom dictionary
to know what to transcribe
for hard to transcribe words.
And it'll be able to talk to Quora
to say,
okay, what are the kinds of words
that I should pre-fill
in the custom dictionary?
So we're going to have
the ability for all of our products
to talk to each other.
By the end of Q2,
we're going to have
a central concept
of who our users are
and what they care about.
So we're going to basically
gather all the context
from what you write,
what you say to your computer,
your emails,
and your files,
and build a view for you
of who you are
and what you care about
that goes into all of our apps,
goes into our content,
and that you can take with you
to chat to your cloud
to enhance the context
that they have about you.
By the end of Q3,
what I want to do
is use all of this
to make our content
more personalized and better.
It's very important to me
that we keep the human soul,
the human storytelling
as the core of every.
And I think it's clear
that it's weird
for everyone
to get the same newsletter
every day.
And if we really want
to keep you on the edge of AI,
we need to know
what you care about
and then tailor
what we tell you about
to what you care about.
And the last thing is,
by the end of Q4,
I think you'll be able
to see the ecosystem
not as an ecosystem
of apps and content,
but as an ecosystem
of agents
that all know about each other
and all collaborate really well
to help you get your work done.
I think a couple other things
that we really want to do,
we really want to be
the number one place
where people go
to learn, to code,
write, and design with AI.
I think we're on our way there,
but there's always more work to do.
I really also think
that the writing that we do,
right now the audience is humans,
but it needs to be
both humans and agents.
So a really good example
is we write a lot
about compound engineering,
which is our
engineering philosophy.
We have a CloudCode plugin
that teaches CloudCode
about compound engineering.
That's an example
of writing for both humans
and for agents.
I also want to be in a place
where by the end of the year,
we're all pushing
to each other's apps,
and that's already happening.
Everyone is committing code
to everyone else's apps,
but there's a lot
that needs to be done.
There's a lot of organizational stuff
to make sure
that everyone's repo
is set up well
to allow this kind of collaboration.
There's also a lot of etiquette
to be done about
when you should submit
a new feature
or bug fix to an app
and how to do it
to take the pressure off
or the work off
of the app GM
in order to allow them
to merge it.
So that's really interesting.
And the next level of that,
once we figure that out,
is allowing customers
to essentially write PRs
that we can really detail
bug reports
or feature specs
that we can then
one-shot with Cloud.
And I think that would be really cool.
So that's where
we're trying to go.
I want to talk for a little bit
about why this is even important.
Why are we doing this?
The world just changed recently.
Right now,
software agents are great.
That's crazy.
And the really interesting thing
is a couple companies,
Anthropic is a big one of them,
that made this bet
that if you make
a great software agent,
it becomes a really good
general agent.
And I think that's true.
And we're seeing that
with Cloud Code
and the Cloud Agent SDK.
And this has gigantic consequences
for software,
for writing,
for design,
for company building,
and for really
how we see ourselves
and our role
in the future.
And it is creating
a tremendous amount
of anxiety and FOMO
and excitement
and just people feeling
like I can't keep up
and I don't want
to be left behind
and I don't know
how this is going
to change my job
and all that kind of stuff.
And there's so many good things,
but there's a real need
for people to actually
figure out
how do you live
a more creative,
more human future
with this technology?
I think that's probably
not the people
building the underlying models.
I think that's asking
an oven maker
how to bake a souffle.
It's people on the edge
who are doing work
that need to figure out
how these tools
fit into our lives
and I think
that's why we're here.
It's why we build
this bundled subscription.
If our goal is
to help people learn
to live and work with AI
in a more flourishing,
creative, better,
more human way,
that maps very cleanly
onto the bundle
that we're building.
So you need to spread the words.
You need to tell stories
about the future
that we see,
that we live in.
You need to build tools
that they'll use
and the tools that we sell
are tools that we build
for ourselves
and then we need
to teach them hands-on
and those are all
the components
of the company
that we're building
and I hope that
we have an opportunity
to be an archetypal
AI native company
and what that means
to me is
we figure out
for ourselves
how to build
and work
and live
in this new future
and then we become
an example
for other people
to follow
and in doing that
they subscribe
to read our ideas
and they use
the tool set
that we build
and all that kind of stuff
and my hope then
is that creates
the way that people
build and write
and think
in this new future
and that's really exciting
and I think
also very important
to me
and I think
we're in this moment
that I want to talk
about for one second
I've seen a lot
of technology waves
when everyone
first started in 2020
it was right before
the creator economy wave
and I was seeing
our numbers
just go up
and I was like
okay there's something
really special here
that's happening
we're growing super fast
I had that tingle feeling
and that's one of the reasons
why we really
went all in on the company
in 2022
one day
I think I'd be away
it was just GPT-3
but I was like
this is the next big thing
and after ChatGPT
we just really
focused the whole company
around AI
and that has really
paid off
and I am getting
that same feeling
right now
and that feeling
is about
what I call
agent native apps
which is basically
apps that are
cloud code
and a trench coat
there's a lot more detail
about what makes
something agent native
and how traditional software
fits into that
I think that cloud code
and trench coat metaphor
should tell you
most of what you need to know
and there's
a ginormous number
of implications for it
but
we're going all in
on that in 2026
and that means
the content that we write
the stuff that we build
all that stuff is
going to be really
focused around this
and yeah
that's it
that's our 2026 strategy
thanks for watching