Domestic helper bots are coming.
Billions is being poured into this new
AI frontier.
A global gold rush underway.
Go make us a cup of coffee.
But how close actually are we to
the sci-fi dream of a robot butler?
Oh, holy, I've never seen this in my
whole life.
Actually, let us start with another
task and we will come back to this.
Good accuracy.
Oh, I spoke too soon.
So this is it, but
it's a normal house on a normal street.
But that kind of makes sense, doesn't
it? They're building a robot for homes.
Hi, Bipasha, how are you?
Good, how are you?
Can you describe what we're
seeing here then?
So you've got the robot off camera,
there's someone wearing some
of the similar kit.
How's it all working?
So we have
a teleoperator who
is wearing a
suit to teleoperate the robot.
Ideally, it should have its own mind.
I mean, it sees a mess.
It should be able to go and clean it up
because it thinks it's messy.
And it should know what to do.
Right now, it is getting
trained to do that.
As an MIT robotics dropout, Bipasha
spun out a student project, quickly
convincing investors to put money into
her vision.
We believe today people have
two aspirations, usually like a car and
a house.
In the future they'll have three
aspirations, a car, a house and a
robot.
A few miles away, also in Palo Alto,
another company has trained its bot to
do some tasks completely on its own.
.
Tony, how's it going?
Wow, it's a home.
Tony Zhao began working on his home
robot while at uni, but dropped out
to build Memo full-time.
Hi, I'm Memo your future home robot
here at Sunday.
So can it
see me around it?
Yeah it can.
Right now it doesn't react to you, but
it can perceive the world with all the
cameras and other sensors.
Can you just go make us a cup of
coffee?
It's after 2 p.m.
Would you like me to go ahead and make
that cup of coffee for you?
Yes, please go ahead.
I'm on it.
Making your coffee now.
So Tony, can I just check with you?
There's no one that we can't see
doing this for the robot.
This is all autonomous.
Yes, it's one single neural network
controlling the whole body movement.
It was all going smoothly,
then Tony paused the demo as he
saw something was off.
Maybe we need to restart this.
Can I restart this?
I think there is a...
Can you stop it?
I think we might need to do it
again. I saw there is some peeling off
here. Sorry about that.
Let's just try again.
Maybe I'm overly cautious.
Oh, holy, oh,
I've never seen this in my whole life.
After a reset, Memo smoothly cleared
away the table.
There's obviously work to be done to
get it ready for homes, but there's no
doubt this is one of the most capable
bots in the world.
How have you got the robot to
be this advanced?
How have done it?
Normally, the way we train AI is
to tele-operate the robot in
people's homes or in other places and
gather the data and train the AI.
And what we're doing is different, as
in we don't need robot data to train
the robot. And instead, we build these
gloves. And people just wear their
gloves in their homes and collect data
for us. And that give us really diverse
data because we now see like more than
500 homes.
And also all the different ways they go
about doing the task.
Sunday's army of robot teachers are all
being paid to do repetitive,
everyday tasks, a reminder of the
human drudgery underpinning how these
machines learn.
The staff allow cameras and sensors to
record their every move at home, but
Sunday plans to start shipping memos
next year, so if the
bot needs to be remotely controlled it
will raise privacy considerations for
customers, as well as questions about
safety in a domestic setting.
Like, they will be kids running around,
kids will be climbing on the robot,
right? So we really want to make sure
that we put safety
as the most fundamental consideration
when we design these robots.
Some robotics companies are already
out in the wild, gathering training
data in public.
Isaac's been trained by watching
hundreds of hours of laundry folding.
For the last couple of months though,
it's been doing it on its own for real,
here, and in six other sites in San
Francisco.
Deployment is the strategy.
Nothing counts if it's sequestered
away in a lab.
This is the very task that we'll also
be doing in homes.
And here we get to prove that it works
in the real world, bring down the time
per article of clothing that we mold.
Here's a t-shirt, we'll do a live
demonstration. There we are, okay.
So this is a lot slower than a human.
So some people might be watching this
saying, oh, that's not very impressive,
but can you tell us why it is
impressive?
It is impressive because this thing can
run all day.
You often hear that robots are best
suited to tasks that are dull, dirty,
or dangerous.
We wanna make clothing folding
optional for people.
Oh, here we go.
Hang on a second.
Struggling with a little bit at the end
there.
You know, we kind of
care about getting a
presentation right.
That is way better than I would do it.
When you first put this robot here,
how long did it take to do one t-shirt?
I think that we were looking at 2-
2.30.
So already what, in how many
months?
That's in a month and a half.
In a month and a half, you've got down
to 1.30, just over 1.30.
We've planned to start shipping Isaacs
to homes this year.
They say it'll be able to tidy up and
fold laundry, but it's not clear how
much of that will be autonomous.
I actually didn't know how to do it
properly until I saw this.
Across town, at Physical Intelligence,
they're not interested in building
robots themselves.
They're focused on creating the AI
software that can be used to make any
robot capable of doing chores
autonomously.
The rest of AI, like in ChatGBT
for example, we're used to
training these models on an internet
of data, but we don't have that web
of data for robotics.
So we want to be able to actually, kind
of essentially breathe intelligence
into any sort of physical embodiment,
whether that's kind of a standard
typical robot, a humanoid robot,
or even something that looks closer to
an appliance, for example.
Like all these companies, Chelsea and
her team are developing their AI
software using reams of videos of
humans doing chores.
Their approach is proving successful.
Investors like AI giant OpenAI
are on board.
Another tech giant, Tesla, is deep
in development of its own humanoid
robot, Optimus.
But it's not yet clear what it can do.
And it's just not in the US where
people are getting excited about
human-like robots.
Chinese company Unitree is
already dominating the market with its
G1 robot.
Seen here in a demo given to us by
its UK seller, Scan.
This is happening right now.
People are buying them, people are
coding on them and people are
learning.
It's entirely operational.
It's not autonomous at all, as
of yet.
It's hard to get into China to film,
but the humanoid robot industry is so
hot there that the government recently
warned a bubble might be building set
to burst.
What's really interesting driving
around and speaking to all these
robotics companies in Silicon Valley is
there's a lot of confidence.
They think they are building the future
and they're certain it's going to be a
huge moneymaker.
But there's also some nervousness as
well because there's lots of things
that we wanted to film and we wanted to
show, but we can't.
They are scared because, of course,
this is a race, a race to bring
to market a domestic robot.
A company that hopes to be the first is
1X.
The Norwegian-founded company moved
here last year, and millions of dollars
are riding on its spot Neo, becoming a
hit.
We've just walked up to see Neo in
action, and someone is
operating Neo right now and watering
all the plants. I've just been told
this is what they do all day.
So there are people in the office
operating Neo with a
VR headset, carrying out tasks
and testing all day long.
Good accuracy.
Oh, spoke too soon.
So interestingly, Nio is struggling
with this particular handle,
but the team here change the handles
all the time because they're trying to
train the robot different ways to open
different handles.
They had it there.
Founder Bernt Børnich is pushing hard
to get Neo out to homes.
He says thousands of people have
already pre-ordered.
So what can Neo do right now
for me in my home?
Yeah, so let me tell you what Neo does
in my home.
So does a pretty good job of
like tidying.
So like resetting my living room and my
house in general.
Wiping surfaces, like cleaning the
counter, like these kind of things.
And that's all someone with a VR
headset. It's a mix.
It's mix. So in my own, we have
a lot of data.
So a lot other stuff in my can get
automated because we have data there.
Periodically, someone kind of steps in
and helps if the robot does not know
exactly how to move on.
Early adopters will have to be
comfortable then, waiving their
privacy.
But Bernt promises that Neo will be
able to carry out many tasks
autonomously by the time they start
shipping it.
Your first set of customers then, they
have to quite wealthy and they have be
willing for Nio to make mistakes
essentially. Well I don't think they
have quite wealthy, I think.
It's £20,000 isn't it?
I don't know how much it is, £20.000?
Yeah, like, most people have a
car?
so you liken it to a car.
For a very large subset of that, it
will be way higher value than having a
second car.
Getting the right customers is
more important in the beginning.
Distribution with the right customer,
so we can really use these amazing
people that are early adopters to
help us make this work.
Outside of the tech bubble, some,
including the International Federation
of Robotics, think it could take 20
years before domestic bots become
truly useful and accepted.
But we have heard that before about
other futuristic AI technologies.
Fasten you seatbelt please.
In some ways, brand new revolutionary
technology does just sort of creep up
on you. If you think about driverless
cars, I've been talking about driver
less cars in my reporting for a decade
at least, but now they're here.
And they're just sort normal.
In many cities across the US and in
China, driverless car are an
everyday sight.
AI robotics companies are convinced
their tech will go the same way.
And not only will their devices be
truly useful, we'll all eventually
want one in our homes.