[MUSIC PLAYING]
DHAVI HARIHARAN: Hi, I'm Dhavi,
a product manager at Google
DeepMind covering genomics.
I'm joined by Ziga, who leads
our genomics team, Natasha, Tom,
and Jun.
We've just released our recent
work, AlphaGenome in "Nature."
AlphaGenome is a unified DNA
sequence-to-function prediction
model that predicts
the functional
impact of genetic variants.
And today, we wanted to talk
about the science behind it,
why we built it, how it came
about, what we released,
and what we're
excited about next.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Maybe the best
place to start is,
why did we build AlphaGenome?
Ziga, how does this fit in with
the overall mission of the team?
ZIGA AVSEC: So the
mission of the team
is to build an AI system that
will allow us to decipher
the genome sequence.
The genome, or the
DNA, is the source code
that the evolution
has programmed
across millions of
years and millions
of-- for millions of species.
So it's the source code of life.
And deciphering this source
code would have enormous benefit
in health and many other areas.
And one way to measure our
progress towards this goal
is to look at how well we can
predict the effects of mutations
or small changes to the
DNA on molecular mechanisms
of the cell that read this DNA.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: And
why is this important,
AI that helps us understand
and decipher the genome?
JUN CHENG: Yeah, I think
improving our understanding
of the genome has
such a profound impact
on everyone's life if you think
about all the people suffering
from genetic disease.
And, in fact, a large fraction
of the rare genetic disease
remain in diagnosis today.
So AI is actually--
we have so poor understanding
of the genome as a whole.
And AI is such a good
tool to read the genome
and make meaningful predictions
about the genetic mutations.
For me, I think
understanding the genome
and predicting mutations is
one of the most impactful
application AI can make.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: How did you
get interested in this field?
JUN CHENG: I started working
on predicting genetic mutation
during my PhD, and this has
been my interest ever since.
I think when I
joined DeepMind, I
was leading
AlphaMissense project,
which was a method to
predicting the genetic effects
from mutations from the coding
region, which was only 2%
of the genome.
But what about the rest
of the 98% of the genome?
That's why we're presenting
AlphaGenome today.
And this method is focusing on
non-coding part of the genome,
and hopefully share some light
on the [INAUDIBLE] majority
part of the genome.
And also, speaking a
bit more personally,
the reason I got into
biology is because, when
I was at high school, I was
reading a college textbook.
It was describing all these
fantastic and complex,
elegant molecular
mechanisms of life.
That's why I got-- so that's
why I decided I should
work on biology for my career.
And, Tom, what's your
experience there?
TOM WARD: It's
quite great to have
such a multidisciplinary team.
We all come from
different walks of life
and bring different
things to the table.
So I think for me, and
I think other people
who hadn't worked in
biology, I think genetics
is a really fascinating field.
It seems like such an
unexplored problem space.
And being able to work out
what very small changes in DNA
can cause in humans
and other species
is really quite fascinating.
And the field is-- and
especially in machine learning,
the field in
computational biology
seems to be going
really, really fast.
And there's lots of things
going on in that field.
So it's a really
exciting place to work.
ZIGA AVSEC: I can
still remember,
before I joined DeepMind,
I worked on [? vp.net, ?]
which was a tiny network
in today's standards.
It took as input a thousand
base pairs of the DNA
and predicted transcription
factor binding
at very high resolution.
And I was fascinated by how rich
and precise this information
could be at base resolution.
But at the same time,
it felt like very much
a zoomed-in picture
of a specific process.
So when I joined
DeepMind, I wanted
to work on more
complex processes.
So we worked together with
David Kelley at Calico
on predicting gene expression
from DNA sequence, which
is a very difficult problem.
And for that problem,
we had to extend
the length of the sequence
quite significantly in order
to capture as many relevant
pieces as possible.
But in order to do that,
we had to trade off
the resolution that made
[? vp.net ?] so interesting.
So it's always felt like a bit
of a trade-off between these two
things, the sequence
length and the resolution.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: I guess there
have been many other models
pushing this area forward.
What was the real gap
that we were trying
to fill with AlphaGenome?
NATASHA LATYSHEVA: There
have been other DNA
sequence-to-function
models before.
The most similar to
AlphaGenome is probably
Informa, also from this team,
and Borzoi from David Kelley's
group in Calico.
And there's also lots of more
specialized single-task models.
There's SpliceAI
for splice size.
There's Orca and Akita
for contact maps,
Chrome [? vp.net ?] for
accessibility, and so on.
I think the gap that
AlphaGenome has filled
is it's modeling more modalities
in one model than ever before.
The input sequence
length is very long,
and the predictions are
very finely detailed.
So I think it's a really
powerful combination
of these three things,
the modality coverage
megabase of DNA sequence and
single-base resolution outputs
for many of the output types.
I think that makes the
model, yeah, quite useful
for variant effect
prediction and variant
interpretation and, of
course, also the increased
predictive kind of
accuracy across all
these different outputs.
The utility and
convenience point, I think,
is very powerful, actually.
So now with one model, you can
look at the effect of a variant
from many different lenses
and consider the effects
on different layers
of molecular biology.
Whereas, before you might have
had to use many different models
to do that analysis.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DHAVI HARIHARAN: Why did
we need separate models?
Why is it so hard
to do long context,
high-resolution multimodalities
all at the same time?
TOM WARD: DNA
sequence-to-function models
work by basically
taking a chunk of DNA
and getting the model to predict
real-world experimental data.
And so like you
said, the complexity
comes from when you want to
make more longer range sequence
predictions at a
higher resolution
and with lots of different
from modalities, you
kind of run up against these
kind of computational limits
and high-memory
usage, which makes
it very difficult from an
engineering perspective.
And so for AlphaGenome, we were
really keen to try and break
that, those trade-offs, and
try and do all of those things
in a single model.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: And how did you
really get around that problem
then?
ZIGA AVSEC: Yeah,
we ended up using--
we ended up taking the
sequence and splicing it
into different
subsequences and then
using multiple TPUs to process
these subsequences, which are
then much shorter in length.
And that allowed us to use much
less memory on a single TPU.
The key piece we
had to make sure
is that they still
communicate with each other,
so that the TP1 can
still communicate
to the last TPU in sequence.
And so instead of
sampling intervals
in the genome randomly, we
sample them next to each other
and then allowed these
TPUs to talk to each other.
I can still remember the
day when we were having
lunch with my colleague, Guido.
And I shared this idea with
him, and we started discussing.
And at the end of the lunch,
we weren't really sure
if it's going to work.
A few days later, he
comes to me and says,
I have a prototype
running with fake data,
and it runs almost as fast as
our informer training loop,
and it can process these
very long sequences
at high resolution.
And at that moment,
I was really excited
because I knew that
this can theoretically
break this limit of long
sequence and high resolution.
Although, in practice,
it turned out
that we were still quite far
away from making it actually
work, right, Tom?
TOM WARD: Yeah, so once we
got the model parallelization
working, the next
thing we needed to do
was be able to feed this model
with vast amounts of training
data.
I think at one point,
we were loading
kind of 40 or 50
gigabytes of data
to try and keep up with
the model's training.
So we had two big realizations.
One was that the data was
actually really sparse.
It's kind of 99% zeros
in some of the modalities
that we were training for.
So that meant that, actually,
all we really needed to focus on
was being able to compress
and decompress the data as
fast as possible.
And so by doing that,
we managed to break
that loading the data
fast enough for the model
to be able to feed it and train.
And then the second
thing we did was
we were really
ruthless on the data
that we were feeding
the model to train.
We did kind of a pass--
a couple of quality check
passes to make sure the data
was either really high quality
or it was added to the
diversity of the model
so that it could get--
train, generalize, a bit more
or learn new capabilities.
So once we got the
data loading working,
we were able to then train
the model really efficiently
and be able to iterate on the
modeling as much as possible.
And so we kind of got the 1D
representation of data training
and predicting.
And so the next thing we were
really excited about working on
was two-dimensional data, so
content maps and splicing.
So, Jun, I think you worked
quite a lot on splicing.
It was definitely a
very tricky problem.
JUN CHENG: Right.
That was quite tricky.
So splicing is a process
that is needed for a gene
to express a protein properly.
And it's a process-- the
genetic information encoded
on the genome non-contiguously.
So if you want to express
a functional protein,
you need to bring all these
non-contiguous information
together.
And that process
is called splicing.
As you can imagine,
this process can easily
go wrong due to
genetic mutations.
And, in fact, many
genetic diseases
are caused because
of splicing defect.
I worked on this
problem during my PhD,
and the method
[INAUDIBLE] published then
was called MS Splice.
We're trying to model the
competition between junctions,
but the model wasn't
nearly as good.
So I had these ideas how to do
this properly back in my mind.
And when we started
working on AlphaGenome,
I realized that this is
a perfect, natural fit.
And with the talent team,
Guido, and Tom, and others,
we finally have all the
technical pieces together
to properly do
this modeling work.
And, yeah, speaking of that,
it wasn't really that easy
as it sounds because the
output format and input
format was quite different.
And we were predicting these 2D
extremely sparse arrays instead
of 1D track.
And, yeah, in the end, we
finally got it to work.
And I'm really, really
happy with that.
And this kind of capability
is actually new to the field.
It's definitely also
new to the team.
And, yeah, after
we get this part
work, and the next big part is
about contact map and, Natasha,
how we made that work.
NATASHA LATYSHEVA:
Yeah, contact maps.
So contact maps are
two-dimensional matrices
that capture interactions
between DNA regions.
And it turns out
these interactions
are very important for gene
regulation, essentially.
So the genome in the
nucleus is folded
in these intricate
three-dimensional shapes.
And the proximity
between regions
is really important
for things like
promoter-enhancer interactions.
So these are two types
of regulatory regions,
which can massively impact
a gene's expression.
And then there's also insulator
elements that specifically
prevent these interactions.
And so these are fundamental
biological processes.
And it's a bit of biology
that we definitely
wanted in the model.
So yeah, luckily, we
managed to add it in
and get it training end-to-end.
And actually, we were happy to
see that adding this modality
didn't lead to any degradation
on the other modalities
we already had.
ZIGA AVSEC: Well, it was
quite interesting to see that,
how we were able to add these
modalities, both 1D modalities,
as well as then 2D modalities,
like splicing and contact maps,
without hurting the model's
performance or slowing it down
significantly.
In the hindsight, it
kind of makes sense
because all of these
modalities or measurements
are measuring the same
underlying process,
like transcription or splicing.
However, it's still nice
that this worked out.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: And as you
add all these new modalities,
how do you check it's
not hurting performance?
How do you evaluate it?
NATASHA LATYSHEVA: Our
evaluation strategy was kind of
in two halves, two-pronged.
The first is checking,
how well does the model
do on new DNA sequences
that it's never seen before?
How accurately can it predict
all these different modalities,
all these different signals
along the DNA sequence?
The second half, which we think
is more interesting, certainly,
for downstream
applications is, again,
variant effect prediction.
So given a small mutation
in the DNA sequence,
this might cause
downstream changes.
And how well can the
model recapitulate that?
The way that we do
this is, basically, we
have two DNA strings, one with
a mutation and one without,
so just the reference
genome sequence.
We feed that into
the model separately.
We get predictions out.
And then we basically
look for differences.
We look for differences
and we summarize them.
So conceptually, at
least, it's fairly simple.
But technically, this
caused endless headaches.
Essentially, the first
thing that we ran into
was speed, actually.
So the model outputs are
something like 11 gigabytes.
And variant scoring
was notoriously slow.
TOM WARD: Yeah, so very
much in the same vein
that we had with feeding
the model data, the next one
we had was basically trying to
get these large predictions back
and summarize them into
useful splice statistics
that we could use to
evaluate how well it's
doing on a particular task.
And so we kind of realized
that everyone on the team
was kind of doing it in
their own little way.
They were coming up with their
own aggregation strategies
and doing it in script
and on notebooks.
But it was, like you
said, really slow.
It would take,
sometimes, minutes
to make these predictions.
And so a few engineers
kind of sat down
and we kind of worked
out how to create
this kind of variant
scoring API, where
we could make these
variant predictions
and aggregate them
on the same devices
that we were training--
running the model.
And that meant that we could
do it really fast and really
efficiently, and doing lots
of different aggregations
in parallel.
And that allowed us to
do lots of evaluations
really, really fast.
And we did quite a few
evaluations for the paper.
NATASHA LATYSHEVA: Yeah, lots
of evaluations and benchmarks,
and benchmarks and evaluations
stuffed into the paper.
But I think the
reason we did that is
we wanted to evaluate the model
as comprehensively as possible,
really, given constraints of
time, and space, and sanity.
One issue that we ran into
very early on, actually,
was how are we going to
structure our evaluation
strategy?
How do we make sure
that we're doing it
in a rigorous,
comprehensive way?
Because the model does
have so many capabilities,
how do we handle all of that?
And the approach that we took
on was, again, parallelization.
And so, essentially,
what happened
is each individual
would take on one
or two areas, maybe
one or two modalities,
and kind of own that section of
the paper, really, end-to-end.
So they would ingest the
data, design the evaluation,
add benchmarks, make
the paper figures.
And this worked
really well, actually.
And the other thing is that
a lot of these evaluations
were already pre-existing
in the research community.
So in a lot of cases, we could
just ingest them and use them
directly.
So that was extremely helpful.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: You mentioned
different people started
focusing on different areas.
Are there different
classes of evaluation then?
NATASHA LATYSHEVA:
Jun can talk to that.
JUN CHENG: Yeah, exactly.
Whenever possible, we
try to evaluate our model
in different ways.
For instance, we evaluate
on the molecular level
if we recapitulate the
experimental readout well,
and also on the organism
level consequence
if we can predict well a
mutation is going to lead
to higher disease risk or not.
Also, we also try to show as
many examples as possible,
both examples where
the model did well
and examples model did not well.
And this was just one example I
found particularly interesting
that we showed in the paper.
The model was trying to predict
some cancer driver mutations,
and we're very surprised to
find that the model actually
did very well, recapitulate
what the researchers found
in the wet lab.
And that was amazing
to see, that the model
ranks the driver
mutations much higher
than some other random controls.
Yeah, we are quite happy,
and put in the paper.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: Awesome.
Yeah, I guess after
the evaluations,
it was kind of down
to the paper writing.
NATASHA LATYSHEVA: Yes,
just the paper writing.
[LAUGHTER]
DHAVI HARIHARAN: Yeah,
why is the paper so long?
It's practically a novel.
NATASHA LATYSHEVA:
Yes, it's so long.
But I think, inevitably,
it was always
going to be long, just
because the scope is massive,
essentially, or at
least I think it is.
We really wanted to do justice
to all of the other models
that we compared against.
We really wanted
to dive as deeply
as we could into all the
different modalities.
So it is what it is.
And I think we also suffered a
bit from one more eval syndrome.
We're all very
excited in this field.
And people would go off and see
a new paper or a new data set,
and they'd want to
integrate into the model
and add just one more
eval, one more figure.
But I do think the paper
is a lot stronger for it.
So I'm happy that happened.
DHAVI HARIHARAN:
Yeah, and how long
did this whole
process take, I guess,
from that initial prototype
to having the paper?
ZIGA AVSEC: I think the
team has been working
in this area for quite a while.
But if we were to pinpoint that
particular launch conversation
and to when the
paper was published,
it was under two year.
So I think the
team worked really
hard to get to that point.
At some point, we all
got into one room,
put a lot of monitors
on the table,
and we worked together on this.
It was a very exciting time to
do that and to see the progress.
And I'm really
excited and very proud
of the team, what
we all-- how we
came together and were able to
release the model and the API.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DHAVI HARIHARAN: So
I joined the team
when the model was
almost ready and we
were starting to think
about how to share
this with the community.
And there was a real eagerness
to both share something quickly,
but also try to find a way
to make it easier to use.
TOM WARD: Yeah, we were really
quite pleased with how we were--
built this kind of model API
for interacting with our model,
and making predictions, and
evaluating and analyzing
the results.
And I think we quite
quickly realized
that we wanted to make the
same thing available to people
externally as well in as
easy and accessible way as
possible, whilst also keeping
the versatility of being
able to do lots of
different things.
So I think one of the
cool things we did
was basically making this API
available at the same time
as our pre-print.
And the cool thing was
that you can kind of just
open up a notebook,
and make a prediction,
and visualize the
results really quickly
without the need of GPU
or installing drivers
and all the other faff that
comes along with loading
a model from scratch.
I think that was
really powerful.
So we were keen to do
that and see what people--
how people used it.
DHAVI HARIHARAN:
With things like
making it simple
and easy to use,
something that we spend a lot
of time talking about as a team
is also, what is this
actually allowing people
to do at the end of the day?
Jun, what are you
most excited about?
JUN CHENG: Yeah,
there's a couple
of things I'm quite
excited about to see how
the community use AlphaGenome.
I think the first is as
a tool to help scientists
to pinpoint what
kind of mutations
could be harmful to human.
Another is, use this as a tool
to understand basic biology.
If you think about it,
biology is quite complex.
And with this tool,
hopefully, scientists
can start to study--
make predictions
about which part of the
genome is functional,
and which part of the genome
is responsible for regulating
gene expression, and which part
is activated in which cell type.
Things like that, I think,
yeah, this is a fantastic
tool for that purpose.
With our genome, hopefully,
scientists can start using that,
and to maximize the return
with the limited resource
and funding they have,
and, yeah, basically,
to improve scientific research.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: Ziga,
Natasha, you've both been
in this field for a while now.
What are some of the
requests we've gotten?
And has there been
anything surprising here?
ZIGA AVSEC: Yeah,
people had lots of--
quite a few feature requests.
One of the ones where, for
example, people are asking,
can they do not just
single-letter changes
to the genome, but multiple
multi-letter changes,
like insertions, or deletions,
or large structural variants?
And for [? indels, ?]
actually, this is a feature.
We already had it implemented.
It just wasn't highlighted
in our quick start enough.
Although, one user
did find a bug
in this code, which is
actually quite tricky,
and we managed to fix it.
And the other feature
was people were asking,
can they use the
embeddings of the model?
Or can they fine-tune
it on their own data?
Because there's quite a lot
of more interesting data
sets that we weren't
able to include
in our model, right, Natasha?
NATASHA LATYSHEVA: Yeah,
actually, on the data front,
I was intrigued,
maybe not surprised,
by the amount of requests
for additional species,
additional modalities,
and additional cell types.
So as we've sort of
mentioned already,
we've tried to make the model
have reasonably good coverage,
although, not in species.
That's still just human
and mouse for now.
But basically, people want more
capabilities under one roof.
And that makes sense, actually.
I can definitely relate to that.
One thing I wanted
to highlight is
that this type of feedback
signal from the community
is incredibly important to us.
It directly feeds into
what we work on next
and what we build next.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DHAVI HARIHARAN:
Now, for a question
we get asked all the
time, what's next?
JUN CHENG: And if you go to our
website and look at the API,
we're predicting
tens of thousands
of scores per variant,
which is obviously
very hard for scientists
to read and reason.
So we're thinking how we can
summarize all these scores
to a single score per
variant and, basically,
aggregate the scores
as much as possible
so that users or scientists
can make prediction per variant
and look at the scores,
and then pick the--
prioritize a list,
short list, of variants
they want to dive deep into.
And then they can look at the
very comprehensive predictions
per cell types and
tissues, and then
answer the questions that--
which effect this variant come
from, which tissue
the effect come from,
and what genes are [INAUDIBLE]
activated, things like that.
TOM WARD: Yeah, then the
other thing we want to do
is support really
large-scale analysis,
like genome-wide association
studies and things like that.
Currently, the API,
you can make many--
lots of predictions, but
maybe not quite as many
as those kind of really wide,
large-scale studies would need.
So, yeah, we're
looking at basically
trying to maybe pre-compute
as many variants as possible
so people can do those
large-scale analysis much more
easily.
NATASHA LATYSHEVA: And we're
releasing the model weights
as well, of course.
TOM WARD: Yes.
NATASHA LATYSHEVA:
Yeah, we're really
excited to see what
people do with those.
So that can be
anything from playing
with the embeddings,
or fine-tuning,
or extending with new data.
And because the model is
good at so many tasks,
we're just really excited to
see what people use it for.
Hopefully, it can be applicable
to many different, diverse
problems, some of
which we probably never
even thought of before.
DHAVI HARIHARAN: I'm so happy
we're going for all of this.
And, hopefully, hearing it
makes some of our scientists
happy as well.
Ziga, maybe going back
to the team's mission
and how AlphaGenome was
sort of a step towards it,
how are you thinking about
what's next for the model?
ZIGA AVSEC: Yeah, I
think there's still
a lot of headroom
for improvement,
a lot both in terms of
predictive performance,
as well as capabilities.
In terms of predictive
performance,
we'll see how far we get.
And in terms of capabilities,
one of the things I'm excited
about is to leverage these new
amazing single-cell atlases,
such as--
because the technology has
been really evolving quickly
and improving.
And this allows us to measure
not just the molecular processes
at the tissue level, but
at the individual cell type
level within the tissue.
And if we could extend
the model with these,
then I think it would be more
applicable to studying variants
associated with diseases where,
for example, this sort of defect
arises in these
individual cell types.
DHAVI HARIHARAN:
Thanks for watching.
Those were some
of our highlights
on building AlphaGenome
and releasing it.
There's a lot more details
in our "Nature" paper.
And we'd really love
to hear from you
as you start exploring
and using the model,
whether that's interesting
case studies, or gaps, or ideas
that can make the work
more useful for you.
Our user support
team is basically us,
so please get in touch with
us on the Discourse forum.
[MUSIC PLAYING]