So level 1. Alright, google.com. Here's the
logo. Here's the search bar. Oh, and here's
the buttons. Why are you still waiting? Well,
it's because you were missing this. This little
line of text at the bottom. See, when
Google launched, it was incredibly minimalistic compared to
all the other search engines out there. But
because of this, they had a problem. When
they started making user tests in the early
2000s with Stanford students, the students would sit
there for 45 seconds staring at the page
waiting for it to finish loading,
even though it was fully loading. And that's
because all the information. And that's because all
the information was at the top. So how
did they fix it? Well, with this. A
copyright notice that has no legal need to
be there, but it was put there only
to let you know that the page has
finished loading. See, this is only level 1
of the 7 levels of the insane rabbit
hole that is designing and building tech products.
And these levels are what makes the difference
between products that feel really bad, that you
hate using, and products that end up generating
billions of billions of dollars in revenue, and
that end up changing the world. We're going
to go from uncovering the smallest details to
the entire product strategies of some of the
biggest tech companies in the world. But even
here at level 1, there's so much more
that you don't see behind the tech that
you use every day. Take a look at
this. This is a nice rounded interface. So
here for these checkboxes, we're going to match
the style, we're going to make them round.
But now you see that there's a problem.
The app feels broken. And that's because by
making these round,
we made them look like something else that
we're used to. Radio buttons, where you can
only select one option at a time. This
super small difference in how rounded these boxes
are completely changed how we interpret what we
see and what we think we can do
in this screen. And that's because we have
this knowledge in our brain that got reinforced
over thousands of times using technology that this
means only one option and this means that
you can have many. Or take a look
at this. Well, of course, this is a
link
to something. Duh. Well, no. Turns out it
was just some blue underlined text. And the
reason this fell off is that we were
missing this. The mouse cursor changing from the
regular arrow to the little hand that says,
hey, there's an action here. This might seem
like a small detail, but without this, our
interfaces would be completely unusable. Like, for example,
trying to drag some panel without the cursor
becoming their size one. Without this small visual
detail on your cursor, you simply wouldn't be
able to use any desktop computer,
and that's why this has been around from
the beginning since 1987, when it was invented
by Bill Atkinson for the Macintosh app HyperCard.
And it's stuck around to this day. Oh,
and all these interactions that you're seeing, I
build them as full working prototypes using Magic
Patterns, the sponsor of this video. More about
it later. But take a look at these.
These are files on your computer, but the
file names are really long. Now, usually when
you have a really, really long string on
an app, this happens. It gets cut and
these dots, which are called ellipses, appear to
tell you that, hey,
there's more. But now, with this, we cannot
see which one is the file version, for
example. Say, v1 or v2, which usually is
stuff that's at the end of the file
name. We cannot put the ellipses at the
beginning either, because otherwise we lose the file
name more together.
So, for example, here in macOS, when we
try to reduce the size of the window,
the file names get the ellipses in the
center, and letters get progressively cheaped away on
each side of the ellipses centered in the
word. So you can see the start of
the file name and the end of the
file name.
So this means that someone had to manually
go in and write all the code that
calculates how many letters to chip away at
each side of the ellipses just to make
sure this happens.
By the way, that someone is Scott Jensen,
who built this, again, for Apple in the
80s.
See, designing tech is not just about making
things look nice. These seemingly small visual details
won't get noticed by 99% of people,
but it's what makes our tech usable.
But yeah, sometimes they are there just because
they're fun. Like, for example, you drag the
Google Street View yellow guy, and you can
see that he's actually holding on to the
cursor and reacting to gravity as you move
him around.
Why? Well, why not?
And now let's start to go up a
level, because that's when things start to get
interesting.
So say you're on a call with your
bank. They're telling you there is a suspicious
activity on your account, and they need to
verify some information.
So you open your banking app to check,
and you see, this, Revolut, is not calling
you.
The people that built this app made it
so that it's detecting when you're on a
phone call and when you're opening the app
at the same time.
And because one of the most common scams
is someone pretending to be your bank and
asking you to do something in the app
while they're on the phone with you,
Do not read it! Do not read in
the card!
Revolut just tells you. Whoever's on the phone,
well, it's not us.
And this is what Level 2 is all
about. It's not just how things look.
It's the interactions and how they behave.
And more importantly, it's about building behaviors that
feel human.
Like take Google Maps. Your phone has a
touchscreen, and it's perfect for moving around this
map.
You can just drag your finger around.
But zooming in still requires you to pinch
the screen, so it requires two hands.
We're usually trying to navigate around. We're on
a bike.
It's the worst possible time to require us
to pinch stuff.
So you end up doing this weird contortionism
just to zoom in.
But actually, in Google Maps, you can double
tap and hold and drag your finger up
and down to zoom in and out with
one finger.
You can actually do it in almost all
the applications where you can pinch to zoom.
The first time I learned about this, I
was like, I'm sorry, what?
But the problem with this is that while
it definitely goes into the genius category, there
is no way to know that you can
actually do this.
Most people don't even know, but one interaction
that instead gets used billions of times every
single day is this.
You know, when you drag down the top
of a list to refresh.
This interaction is incredibly intuitive, and it removes
the need for an additional refresh button.
But while this looks totally innocuous, today this
feature is used by the biggest social media
companies on the planet,
paired with infinite scrolling feeds, like Instagram, to
show you something new every time you refresh.
And this one simple interaction is probably responsible
for billions of dollars of revenue in ads
on these feeds.
But now, let's go up a level once
again, because in 2008, music streaming had a
problem.
Piracy was everywhere.
People were illegally downloading songs all over the
place.
And if I wanted to purchase my entire
current Spotify library legally on iTunes back then,
it would have run me $3,800.
And I would have to synchronize all these
songs manually on all of my devices.
And that's when Spotify came in.
But they had a problem.
See, they started with this promise of instant
music streaming.
Just choose a track and immediately listen to
it.
But the problem is that internet speeds back
then, especially mobile, weren't anywhere near as fast
as they are today.
They tried what anyone would.
Just host the songs on their servers, and
anytime someone needs a song, just stream it
down to the device.
And it was atrocious.
It could take from 30 seconds to a
full minute for a song to start playing.
So that's when they had an idea.
They bought a company that actually powered piracy.
And that you might remember called uTorrent.
And sold uTorrent almost immediately.
But the reason they did this is to
get this one guy.
Ludwig Strigus.
And he rebuilt Spotify's infrastructure at the time
using the same technology that powered piracy.
Peer to peer.
See, when you play the song, it came
from three places at once.
Spotify servers, your own cash, and other Spotify
users near you.
A 2010 study found that only 8.8
% of the music came from Spotify servers.
36% came from other users, and the
rest was smartly downloaded already on your device.
They took the exact technology that the music
industry were suing people over, and used it
to build a legal alternative.
And as a user, you never noticed.
You just clicked on a song, and it
worked.
See, most people think that great products are
built around great technology.
But most of the times, it's the opposite
that happens.
You have a great idea for how the
perfect interaction and experience looks like, and then
you find the technology that makes it possible.
Because the ones that really matter are those
that make incredible experiences possible.
But also where the technology disappears, and you
never see it.
But as we get to level 4, this
is where we start to get into the
really powerful laws that control how tech products
are designed and built.
And how they can also be used to
manipulate you.
So you just finished an episode on Netflix.
The usual cliffhanger, credits roll, and three, two,
what?
The next episode already started.
See, this was an example of level 4
product design.
And it's something that seems small, but it's
incredibly powerful to control the behavior of millions
of users.
Both in a good and in a bad
way.
Defaults.
Oh look, I got ghosted by a 10
out of 10 on both iMessage and WhatsApp.
Now, other than the fact that I need
more res, there's something else going on here.
On WhatsApp, read receipts are on by default.
But on iMessage, you instead choose if you
want them or not.
Which for the most part would mean that
people turn them off.
Since when presented with the choice, users tend
to choose the option that gives out less
information about them on average.
Now, this might seem like a small difference.
But since most people never change their settings,
this creates completely different social dynamics.
On WhatsApp, seen without a reply is bloated.
You saw my message.
Why didn't you respond?
On iMessage, nobody knows if you read it.
Same feature, different default, different relationship.
This is called default bias.
And it's not just in your tech.
This is a chart of the percentage of
organ donors in different European countries.
Try to guess what is the difference between
the first and the second group.
Well, the only difference is the default choice.
In Austria, the default is to donate.
And you opt out of donating.
Well, in Denmark, you need to opt in
to donate.
And this is, well, default bias.
But here is where defaults become worth billions
of dollars.
Have you ever wondered why did Google buy
Android?
Spent billions to make it a worldwide mobile
operating system only to give it away for
free?
Or why did they build Chrome?
Well, not because they love making browsers or
operating systems,
but because whoever controls the platform can set
the defaults,
including the search engine which they set to
Google, where they make their money.
And for the devices they don't control, Google
pays Apple $20 billion a year
just to be the default option on Safari.
They estimated that they would lose 60%
to 80% of iPhone search traffic if
they didn't do this.
Not because people would switch to Bing, but
because people just use whatever is already there.
Now, see all these examples and visuals that
I've shown you in this very video.
Well, these are real working components made with
the sponsor of this video, Magic Patterns,
because it's built exactly for this.
See, Magic Patterns is not about building entire
apps from scratch,
but it's about allowing builders like me to
quickly try different designs,
iterations and components with natural language just by
chatting.
If you notice, all the examples I made
in this video were also in the same
visual style.
And that's because with Magic Patterns, you can
set your product's styling, colors and visuals,
and have it follow it when prototyping.
You can even upload screenshots as a reference
to guide the AI towards what you're envisioning.
Once you're happy with something, you can export
it straight to Figma,
sync it to GitHub, or deploy it to
a custom domain.
If you're working with a team, there's a
shared canvas for real-time collaboration.
You can join the army of designers, engineers,
thinkers, and product teams,
or the using Magic Patterns with the link
in the description,
which also gives the viewers of my channel
a nice little discount.
But now, let's go back to the video,
because now that we get to level 5,
we start to blur the boundaries between product
design and product strategy.
And this is where you start to see
the more important product decisions that shape how
we use something.
So, let me show you how I personally
used level 5 to build this.
This is Flask.
It's my own company and my own product.
It's a video collaboration tool where you can
collaborate on videos,
record comments, and share your screen.
And all of the comments appear visually right
on the video's timeline.
Now, for every comment, we need to give
out key information that we cannot miss.
For example, who created the comment, Enrico in
this case,
when this was added, or which timestamp it's
referencing in the video.
You also need a way to mark the
comment as done.
Now, the most basic approach that any designer
would take is this.
Find a nice way to get them out,
and you're done.
For example, this is what my main competitor
does.
You have all the info right here, and
you can mark a comment as done right
there.
But instead, what if we take a level
5 strategic approach to this,
where we don't just think about how to
arrange things visually,
but how to architect the logic of the
entire app to make this all much more
elegant.
For example, instead of deciding that this is
a done toggle,
why don't we create the general purpose tagging
system,
where each element can have custom tags.
And then we'll create a default one called
done,
and another one called important.
So we can show users that you can
actually have more than one at a time.
And now, these are not fixed in place.
If you don't like done, and you want
to use it for something else,
you can just delete it.
But as people started to request more and
more features,
they wanted to be able to filter by
user,
or by custom tag, or by creation date,
and it was getting so complicated.
So instead, we're going to make one structural
design change,
and say that everything is a tag.
So now the creator becomes a tag.
The creation time becomes a tag.
Even the link timestamp becomes a tag.
Now, these are not editable by the user,
but watch what happens.
Now I can create a filtering system
that filters by multiple types of tags in
the same place,
and it all feels logical.
Now I don't need to have a dedicated
row up top with its own layout.
I can just have a list of tags.
And now, a while later,
I had to build a system to notify
users of new comments that got added
since they last visited.
Normally, I would have to create an entirely
new view
to show these comments.
But now that we made this structural design
decision
that everything is a tag,
you can see that I just need to
add a tag called new to the comments.
And clicking here will just trigger a filter
for that tag,
which uses all the existing stuff that we
already built before.
Having a great structural design in the logic
of how your app works
makes everything else simpler.
That's why in a similar way to Flask,
Notion took the decision to make everything a
page.
Even though it might be displayed as a
calendar or a feed or a table,
everything is a page.
Or while Slack decided that everything is a
channel.
These are all examples of level 5.
But at level 6 is where we start
to leave product design
as you think about it and start to
enter the realm of product strategy.
See, for example, video has been around forever.
You can record yourself on your phone.
You can have a video call on Zoom.
You can upload to YouTube.
Video is soft.
We don't need any more video products.
But then Loom came along and said,
what if video wasn't for entertainment or for
live calls,
but for replacing meetings?
What if instead of scheduling 30 minutes with
your team,
you just record a 3-minute video and
send it out?
They didn't invent video.
They didn't invent recording.
They didn't invent players.
They reframed what video is for.
And this little reframe built a company that
Atlassian bought for $975 million.
Or take Superhuman.
Email has been around for decades.
Gmail is free.
What could you possibly do here?
Well, Superhuman reframed email from inbox you need
to manage
to the fastest email out there.
They added keyboard shortcuts for everything.
They show you how long it takes to
get through your inbox.
They gamified going to inbox zero.
And that's how they charge $30 a month
for it.
This is what level 6 is all about.
The technology doesn't change.
The framing doesn't change.
Hell, the design might not even change.
But the right strategic decision here
can create billions of dollars worth of company.
And now we finally get to level 7.
This is Steve Jobs kind of territory.
Get rid of all these buttons and just
make a giant screen.
See, at the time, this sounded insane.
Blackberry was king.
Physical keyboards were essential.
The idea that you could type accurately on
a touchscreen
was considered fantasy.
And here's the thing.
It wasn't even a new idea.
In 1984, a company called General Magic
spun off from Apple and shipped the Sonic
Magic Link,
a handheld device with a touchscreen
where you could do email, calendar, notes,
the first smartphone 13 years before the iPhone.
And it flopped.
So what is the difference here?
It's the same vision, the same bed,
but a completely different outcome.
The difference was everything underneath.
General Magic, just like Steve Jobs a few
years later,
had level 7.
It's a crazy product vision.
Something that completely changes things.
But they didn't have all the layers underneath.
And the difference between Steve Jobs and the
iPhone team
and everyone else is all the levels underneath.
It's going to level 6 and reframing the
phone
from a device that makes calls
to a computer in your pocket.
Not a phone with apps, but apps with
a phone.
It's going back to level 5.
The structural decision that everything is an app,
no file system, no complex desktop-like UI,
everything is in this neat grid of apps.
It's going back to level 4, the defaults.
The App Store ships with Apple's apps front
and center.
Safari defaults to Google.
The home button always takes you home.
And of course, you need level 3,
the technical innovation.
Capacitive multi-touch that actually works.
Gorilla Glass that doesn't break.
A battery that lasts a day.
And going back to level 2,
the interactions, inventing pinch to zoom,
slide to unlock,
the rubber band bouncy feel when you scroll
too far.
And all the way to level 1,
the details, the squircles on every icon,
the weight of the animation.
And Ken Cosienta, an engineer with a deadline,
fingered out that you need to make
the invisible hitboxes of the keyboard
dynamically bigger based on the letter you were
typing.
Otherwise, your keyboard wouldn't work.
But what you saw is just the beginning.
This video is part of a series
where we go behind the scenes of the
design,
engineering, and psychology
of the tech that we use every day.
And how even things that look so simple
and stupid
hide an absurd amount of complexity.
And you can find the next video right
here.